<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessednes of Brytaine, or A celebration of the Queenes holyday conteining, a breefe rehersall, of the inestimable benefits, generally had &amp; enioyed, not only all England ouer, but also in forrein partes, through the gracious bountie, and incomparable blessed rule of our royall Queene Elizabeth. Composed, and set foorth, in due reuerence, &amp; ioyfull memoriall, of her Maiesties present entrance into the thirtieth yeere of her most triumphant raigne, with hartie prayer, for the long continuing, and prosperous preseruing of the same: by Maurice Kyffin. Published with authoritie.</title>
            <author>Kyffin, Maurice, d. 1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9805</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04954)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9805)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 346:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessednes of Brytaine, or A celebration of the Queenes holyday conteining, a breefe rehersall, of the inestimable benefits, generally had &amp; enioyed, not only all England ouer, but also in forrein partes, through the gracious bountie, and incomparable blessed rule of our royall Queene Elizabeth. Composed, and set foorth, in due reuerence, &amp; ioyfull memoriall, of her Maiesties present entrance into the thirtieth yeere of her most triumphant raigne, with hartie prayer, for the long continuing, and prosperous preseruing of the same: by Maurice Kyffin. Published with authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Kyffin, Maurice, d. 1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn VVindet, dwelling in Adling streete, at the signe of the White Beare, neere Baynardes Castell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BLESSEDNES OF <hi>BRYTAINE, OR</hi> A Celebration of the Queenes Holyday, Conteining, A Breefe reherſall, of the inestimable Benefits, generally had &amp; enioyed, not only all England ouer, but alſo in forrein Partes, through the gracious Bountie, and incomparable bleſſed Rule of our Royall Queene ELIZABETH.</p>
            <p>Compoſed, and ſet foorth, in due Reuerence, &amp; ioyfull Memoriall, of her Maieſties preſent entrance into the <hi>Thirtieth yeere</hi> of her moſt triumphant raigne, with hartie prayer, for the long continuing, and proſperous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of the ſame: by Maurice Kyffin.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Deum Timete. Regem Honorate.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>2.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Fiant preces pro Regibus &amp; Principibus, vt tranquillam &amp; quietam vitam degamus, cum omnipietate &amp; honeſtate.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>2.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed vvith Authoritie.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by Iohn Windet, dwelling in Adling ſtreete, at the ſigne of the White Beare, neere Baynardes Caſtell.</p>
            <p>1587.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plura Poſthac.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORBLE and Renoumed in all Heroicall Vertues, Sir <hi>Robert Devreux Knight, Erle of Eſſex and Ewe,</hi> Vicount Hereford, and Bourgchier, Lord Ferrers of Chartleigh, Bourgchier and Lovain, and Maiſter of her Maieſties horſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE faithfull loue, and dutie, (Right honorable) long ſince deſeruedly born, by my deceaſed Father, both to your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Noble Graundfather, and likewiſe to the famous and woorthie Erle your Father, (vnto whom for diuers reſpects, he was much bounden being aliue, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, left the like Bond of dutie, in vs his Children towards your Lordſhip) hath the more emboldened me, (preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on your Lordſhips great Courteſies) To publiſh, vnder your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable protection, theſe my vnpoliſhed verſes, of her Maieſtie: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, though I haue but ſhowen my leaden skill, in a <hi>Golden Cauſe,</hi> yet hath the ſame proceeded from ſuch ardent deſire, and deuotion in me, as thereby it may ſeeme, in ſome meane, to merit Tolleration, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſith it carrieth a duitifull remembrance, of her Maieſties moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous and <hi>peaceable</hi> raigne ouer vs: which hauing run the full, and Bleſſed Courſe, of <hi>Nyne and Twentie yeeres;</hi> doth now, begin the <hi>Thirtieth,</hi> to the great ioy, &amp; in ſpeakeable comfort of this her royall Kingdome; In reuerend regard whereof, this poore Poem is moſt chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended: I humbly therefore, preſent it to the Courteous accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your moſt Honorable Lordſhip: Whome I be ſeech the <hi>Higheſt</hi> to bleſſe, and enriche, with increaſe of all perfect Honor, long life, and euer during felicitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Moſt humble at your good Lordſhips commaundment. Maurice Kyffin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:3"/>
            <head>D. P. To the Reader.</head>
            <l>TWO things make blisfull Realmes, <hi>Religion</hi> pure and <hi>Peace:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Which <hi>Two</hi> our England hath enioyd, long time with large increaſe.</l>
            <l>The God of peace be praiſd, who grauntes our Birth and Being,</l>
            <l>In this ſame <hi>Realme,</hi> with this <hi>Rare Prince,</hi> theſe <hi>gladſome Seaſons</hi> ſeeing.</l>
            <l>And pray we God likewiſe, this State ſtill to defend:</l>
            <l>Preſeruing it, in perfect Peace, till that the world take end.</l>
            <l>The Author of this booke, deſerues a during fame,</l>
            <l>Who choſe a good Ground, for his worke, and wrought well on the ſame.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>T. LL. In praiſe of this booke, and the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHo liſt to ſee her Noble deeds diſplaid,</l>
               <l>Whoſe golden gifts, eche creature doth adore,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Vertues Rare, haue hauty harts diſmaid,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Name, and Fame, encreaſeth more &amp; more:</l>
               <l>Let them peruſe this Poem, with Aduiſe.</l>
               <l>By <hi>Kyffins</hi> pen, put down in perfect wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A work of woorth, beſeeming well his Arte,</l>
               <l>So fitly framd, and fraught, with tryed Truthe.</l>
               <l>As may Reioyce, eche loyall ſubiects hart,</l>
               <l>To heare, and ſee; which hidden had bin Ruthe.</l>
               <l>Our Queenes long Raigne, to our ſtill during ioy,</l>
               <l>The King of Kings, preſerue free from Annoy,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>J. H. In commendation of this worke, &amp; the writer.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Perſian <hi>Cyrus, Xenophens</hi> penne, <hi>Achilles, Homers found:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>King <hi>Alexanders</hi> valure great, did <hi>Curtius</hi> ſtile reſound,</l>
               <l>Their worthie fame, thoſe worthie wittes, to skies aloft do ſend,</l>
               <l>Thoſe worthie wits, cake by their fame themſelues to fame commend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though skilfull Muſes notes, come ſhort to ſound this Princes prayſe,</l>
               <l>Her Princely giftes, her Iuſtice mylde, her Peacefull laſting dayes:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Kyffins</hi> Muſe in ſtately ſtile, hath ſhot ſo neare the ſame,</l>
               <l>That by reſounding worthie praiſe, himſelf deſerueth fame.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>R. Cooke, in commendation of his friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Kyffin.</head>
            <l>THe frutefull Muſes ſeeme, to haue conſpird, with full aſſent,</l>
            <l>Vplifting <hi>Kyffins</hi> lore, with weightie woords to work Content:</l>
            <l>The ſubiect of his Verſe, is ſacred, firme, and full of grace,</l>
            <l>Whereon his Web is wrought, whoſe learned skill, none can deface,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Momus</hi> the carping God, to Cauill here can finde no cauſe,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Zoylus</hi> ſpitefull wretch, hath here wherewith to ſtop his iawes.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:3"/>
            <head>THE BLESSEDNES OF BRYTAINE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PEarce <hi>Clio Muſe,</hi> my weake, vnwoorthie wit:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caliope,</hi> ſet foorth my ſtile with ſtrength;</l>
               <l>Vnfold her <hi>Fame</hi> (with words foorth ſounding fit,)</l>
               <l>Whome <hi>Kings</hi> adore, &amp; <hi>Lords</hi> in worldly length:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe Sacred Hand the <hi>Stately Scepters</hi> hold,</l>
               <l>And Royall, Rules her Realmes in <hi>Crowned gold.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Monarch Mayden Queene</hi> adorned rare,</l>
               <l>VVith Regall Heauenly dowres, of diuers kinde;</l>
               <l>In whome, who liſt <hi>dame Natures Workes</hi> compare,</l>
               <l>VVith thoſe rich <hi>Thewes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vertues</hi> of her Minde,</l>
               <l>Shall much admire, at ſuch a <hi>Myrrour</hi> ſheene,</l>
               <l>At ſuch a <hi>Prince,</hi> at ſuch a <hi>Peereles Queene.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Starre</hi> of VVomen Sex, <hi>Graue Wiſedoms ſtore:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sententious, ſpeaking Tongs in filed phraze,</l>
               <l>Profoundly learnd, and Perfect in eche Lore,</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Fame,</hi> no Rav'ning Time, ſhall euer Raze:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hater</hi> of <hi>Wrong, high Refuge</hi> eke for <hi>Right,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Concord,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> continuing by her Might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat ſhould I <hi>Nymphs,</hi> or <hi>Goddeſſes</hi> Recount?</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Aegypt Queenes,</hi> or <hi>Romane Ladies</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Befides that ſuch manner of Reciting ſtrange and Hetheniſh Names, were here altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor doth alſo of very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſhun that bea ten high way, to fil paper with peſtring Names of fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gods, Goddeſſes, Nymphs, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Romans, &amp;c. Being a thing of ſome ſomtimes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, too too much, and to little effect.</note> name?</l>
               <l>Sith as Supreme, <hi>our Sov'raigne</hi> dooth ſurmount,</l>
               <l>In choice of <hi>Good,</hi> the cheefe of all thoſe ſame?</l>
               <l>For to compare the <hi>Great,</hi> with ſimple <hi>ſmall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is thereby, not to praiſe the <hi>Beſt</hi> at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Large Light of <hi>Sov'raigne Seat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhoſe <hi>Iuſtice, Prudence, Temprance, Fortitude,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ingrafted yong, are grown foorth ſpreading Great,</l>
               <l>Throughout the world, mong Nations wiſe &amp; rude:</l>
               <l>No land, but laudes this <hi>right Reſplendant Roſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tutor</hi> to <hi>Frends,</hi> and <hi>Terror</hi> vnto <hi>Foes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>As <hi>Shyning Sunne</hi> recleeres the darkned Skye,<note place="margin">The reeſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the Goſpel, by her Maieſtie, a work of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable worth, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for euer and euer. <hi>Primaris Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipis Cura, Religio.</hi> Dauid. 1. P. 13. Aſa. 2. Par. 14. Ichoſ. 2. P. 17. Iooſh. 2. p. 23. Ioſias, 2. Reg. 22. Hezechiah, 2 Par. 29.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And foorth recalles eche thing, from ſhiv'ring Shrowds,</l>
               <l>So hath our <hi>Second Sunne,</hi> both farre and nye,</l>
               <l>by brightning Beames, <hi>outcleerd erronious Clouds:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Apow'rfull Prop of <hi>Chriſtes Euangell</hi> pure,</l>
               <l>One whoſe Support, it reſts Repoſed ſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our <hi>Currant Coyne</hi> was Mettall baſe and meane,<note place="margin">Argentum tuum Scoris. Iſaiah. <hi>1.22.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Till her moſt princely <hi>Grace,</hi> the ſame put out,</l>
               <l>By perfect Gold, and pured Siluer cleane,<note place="margin">Baſe Coynes aboliſhed by her highnes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>VVhich paſſe for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Coynes, her Realms throughout.</l>
               <l>A Deede, deſeruing her Perpetuall Praiſe,</l>
               <l>And Publik Profit, to this Land alwaies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ad hereto <hi>Armour,</hi> and <hi>Artillery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The royal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, by her Maieſtie for the defence of the Realme. <hi>Foelix eſt ea Reſp. quae tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore pacis, Bella inactat. Laur. Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nal. de optimo Senatore fol.</hi> 71.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Of her moſt Royall Charges cheefely found;</l>
               <l>As ſtore of <hi>Arming ſteele</hi> defenſiuely,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Roring Gunnes,</hi> far rendring fired ſound;</l>
               <l>A furth'ring Strength for <hi>Peace,</hi> and ſafe Repoſe:</l>
               <l>And Meanes, reſiſting Rage, of <hi>Warring foes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>I may not here omit in Silent ſorte,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Nauie Royall, built &amp; maintained by her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</hi> Pericles A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ait: Vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pecunia para<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da rationem put and am, Naues quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plurimas ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, alias ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro extra eam rationes, nal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius momenti exiſtimandas.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Her <hi>Royall Ships</hi> ſtrong wrought for <hi>ſtearnful warre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(VVhereof all worldly Realmes do raiſe Report)</l>
               <l>Through raging Seas diſcouering Regions farre:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Scowre-ſea Nauy</hi> all bright &amp; brauely burniſht</l>
               <l>Foorth ſpowting fire, faire, huge, and fully furniſht.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen flooriſht <hi>Learning</hi> to ſuch <hi>Type of height?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plentiful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all kind of learning, &amp; right whol ſome lawes, enioyed by her Maieſties moſt gracious meanes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>purefull Preaching,</hi> when had it more place?</l>
               <l>VVhen was <hi>Gods worde</hi> ſo knowne to euery weight,</l>
               <l>VVhich heretofore, did ſuffer ſuch Deface?</l>
               <l>VVhen raignd <hi>Religion</hi> ſo deuoyd of cryme?</l>
               <l>Or rightfull <hi>Lawes,</hi> as in her Royall tyme?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen was this Realme ſo rich of glittring <hi>Gold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Realme wonderfully enriched with Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. The earth moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly bleſſed with ſertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, And eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enioying his own, vnder her highnes proſperous gouetnement.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>plated Siluer, pearle,</hi> and <hi>precious ſtones?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhen was more <hi>Tillage</hi> on this fertile Mold?</l>
               <l>Or more riche ſtreaming Graces growne at ones?</l>
               <l>Or more <hi>Concordant life,</hi> in Country and Towne,</l>
               <l>Then ſince her <hi>Regall Highnes came to Crown?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her Sacred Senate</hi> by their graue foreſight,<note place="margin">The vigilant Care, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant trauell of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable priuy Councel.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Prouide for <hi>Publik Good</hi> and <hi>Ev'ls</hi> preuent,</l>
               <l>Conſeruing <hi>Common weale,</hi> from Perils plight,</l>
               <l>In Rightfull Ruling, Concord, &amp; Concent:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Senate</hi> well beſitting Such a Charge;</l>
               <l>Prudent, &amp; prompt in Lore and Wiſdome large.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From Wrathfull <hi>VVarre,</hi> her People reſt in <hi>Peace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The moſt bleſſed and peaceable ſtate of her Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, round about them. Strangers gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeued by hae Highnes, within her own king, dom.</note>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>waſting VVoes,</hi> her Subiects liue Secure:</l>
               <l>And yet our Neighbour Nations VVarres not ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Their dire distreſſe, and wailfull VVoes ſtill dure;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Moſt of Might,</hi> eke makes her Realm a Towre</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strangers</hi> to ſhield, from many a balefull Showre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Mightie Queene,</hi> pure with Compaſsion preſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Her Maieſties gracious aide vnto her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed neigh bours abroad.</hi> Regia (credo mibi) res eſt ſuccurrere laplis, Conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit vt tanto, quantus es ipſe viro. Ouid. li. <hi>2.</hi> do Pon.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Rendring Reliefe, to Neighbour freends forlorn:</l>
               <l>Her helping Hand, holds vp the weake distreſt,</l>
               <l>And hath the haughtie, dreadfull, oft downborn:</l>
               <l>VVhereof Records, full rife re naining ſtore;</l>
               <l>Note <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> Belgia, and many places more.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lib'rall Rewarder</hi> of <hi>Heroicall</hi> Acts;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Her Highnes bountiful li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie. Her Mercy towardes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</hi> Imperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus potiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Nempe, Proemio &amp; Pana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> teſte So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Iuſticia ſine Miſericordia Crudelitas. Miſericordia ſine Iuſtitia fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ittas.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Ritch in Reward, large giuing Gwer dons great;</l>
               <l>Prone eke to pardon, many offending facts,</l>
               <l>Yea though the ſame, concern her <hi>Regall Seat;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rigor</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> in Reuenging Lawes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mylde</hi> by her <hi>Mercy,</hi> wreaks not eche Cauſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Bleſſed Branch of <hi>Brutus</hi> Royall Race;<note place="margin">Her Maieſtie Princeſſe of Wales, where the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants enioy Gods worde in their own language, through the meere grace &amp; goodnes of her highnes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Brytiſh wightes</hi> a Blisfull worldly ioy,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Puiſſant Princeſſe</hi> of Their Natiue place,</l>
               <l>To ſhield their Earthly liues from all annoy:</l>
               <l>And to their Sickly Soules, a Sov'raigne Leche,</l>
               <l>Graunting <hi>Chriſts Goſpel,</hi> in their Country ſpeche.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Princely Poſſeſſor</hi> of this Realme full Right,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Heire apparant</hi> to the <hi>Heav'nly Crown:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aſsigned to ſerue <hi>Gods Truthe,</hi> with Maine &amp; Might</l>
               <l>Vpraiſing <hi>Vertue, Vice</hi> depreſsing downe:</l>
               <l>Frutefull in <hi>Faith,</hi> though fruteles, wanting feere:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such</hi> brings ſhee<note n="*" place="margin">A perpetual memory of her manifold goodnes, in ſteade of Sonnes and daughters. <hi>Praferre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                           <desc>••…</desc>
                        </gap> liberis Regem decet. Seneca in Tr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Frute,</hi> in ſtead of Children heere.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such</hi> Rare, Renowmed <hi>Deeds,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Omnis la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> virtutis in Actione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtis Ariſt.</note> our <hi>Queene</hi> hath don</l>
               <l>And more than my poore powre may well expreſſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Violenta ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Imperit continuit diu. Sen. in T.</note> Long hath her Raigne, this <hi>Glorious Race</hi> foorth run</l>
               <l>Long may it laſt, foorth bringing frutes no leſſe:</l>
               <l>Great is the <hi>Good,</hi> thus grown foorth, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>her Grace:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great good</hi> ſhal grow, through her like le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthned ſpace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Owretched Wights, that would this <hi>Queene</hi> enharme,<note place="margin">A reproof vnto Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</note>
               </l>
               <l>By cloſe contryuing of her Cruell Death;</l>
               <l>VVhat curſed <hi>Circes,</hi> could their mindes ſo charme,<note place="margin">They rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me Euill for Good: for they haue pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uily laid their Net to deſtroy me without cauſe. Pſalm. 35.</note>
               </l>
               <l>As not to recke, to reaue their <hi>Liege</hi> of breath?</l>
               <l>Fell Raging <hi>Rome,</hi> all this is long of thee,</l>
               <l>From whome, no Troubling Treaſons, here are free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our <hi>kingly Rooted Roſe,</hi> freſh flowring ſtands;</l>
               <l>Garded by <hi>Gods</hi> great Powre, and Prouidence:</l>
               <l>A maſing much, all Traitours trembling hands,</l>
               <l>VVhich plye to pluck this <hi>Plant</hi> by violence:</l>
               <l>Yea<note n="*" place="margin">Magna eſt veritas, &amp; Prau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>let. <hi>Eſdras. 3. c. 4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Truthe</hi> downe treading <hi>Treaſon</hi> vnto ſhame,</l>
               <l>Victor ſuruiues, by vanquiſhing the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Thriſe happie <hi>Land,</hi> whoſe Sov'raigne Ladies life,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lord</hi> enlengthning, ſaues from ſoddein haps;</l>
               <l>Though Ciuile Bronds, and forrein Furies rife,</l>
               <l>Conioyning erſt, haue threatned <hi>Thunder claps,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet Maugre <hi>Malice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Si Dent nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, quis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Nos. Paul. <hi>8.</hi> Rom.</note> Foes are put to foyle,</l>
               <l>And ſafe remaines, our <hi>Sov'raigne,</hi> &amp; our <hi>Soyle.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thriſe happy <hi>Queene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Angel of the Lord tarryeth about them that fear him, and that put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir truſt in him. Pſal. 34. There is no King that can be ſaued by the multitude of an Hoſte, &amp;c. Behold the Eye of the Lord is vpon them that fear him, and that put their truſt in his Mercy. Pſal. 33.</note> acknown of <hi>God</hi> ſo deere,</l>
               <l>Gainſt whome, what ſecret Miſcheefs haue bin ſought,</l>
               <l>But that the ſame, would preſently appeere,</l>
               <l>By meanes <hi>Miraculous,</hi> as yet vnwrought?</l>
               <l>A Sured Signe, whome <hi>God</hi> protects to <hi>Ioy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>lurking Ev'l,</hi> can thereto worke Annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Glorious Ruler</hi> of the gliſtring <hi>Hev'n,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Prolong her Health, with Heapes of happie Yeeres,</l>
               <l>That as her Rule hath Raignd twiſe <hi>Lev'n</hi> &amp; <hi>Sev'n,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The prayer &amp; wiſh of all good Sub.</note>
               </l>
               <l>So may ſhee ſtill, ſurpas all Potent Peeres,</l>
               <l>To liue, and long time wield the Ciuile ſwoord,</l>
               <l>As far, as courſe of Nature can affoord.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Far <hi>Forrain lands,</hi> be are witneſſe of her <hi>Name;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Far <hi>ſurging Seas,</hi> haue felt her warlik Ships;</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Seas,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lands,</hi> foorth thunder out her <hi>Fame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fama manet fact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, poſito velamine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt; Et me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem Fama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui bene geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit habet. Ouid. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. Faſt.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Through force of flowring Acts, free from Ecclips:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizabeths</hi> due praiſe ſhall neuer dye,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Earth,</hi> nor <hi>Seas,</hi> nor in the <hi>ſtarrie Skye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Right <hi>Reu'rend Princeſſe,</hi> rare is thy Renown,</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Spitefull Enuie,</hi> ſpue foorth poyſned gall;</l>
               <l>Naught ſhall it craſe, thine Acts <hi>Eternall Crowne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor miniſh much, thy ſound ſucceſſe at all:</l>
               <l>No Beſt may ſhunne fell<note n="*" place="margin">Ars prima Regni, eſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Inuidians pati. Sence. in Here. fur.</note> Enuies ſowrfull ſtench,</l>
               <l>VVhom <hi>Kezars, Kings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Queenes,</hi> haue faild to quench.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As Higheſt Hils, bide fierceſt force of VVeather,</l>
               <l>And Tall Trees tops, be are greateſt ſtreſſe of VVinde,</l>
               <l>As fineſt Blacke, yelds ſhowe of ſmallest fether,</l>
               <l>And in Pure VVhite, the leaſt black More we finde:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Enuies</hi> ſhaft, is ſhot at<note n="*" place="margin">Summa petis liuor, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flant altiſsima venti. Ouid.</note> 
                  <hi>Higheſt Marke;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And pries in <hi>Pureſt Things,</hi> whereat to barke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>No <hi>Ruler Such</hi> hath weld this Realme of yore,</l>
               <l>Fewe Realmes haue ioyd, ſo long a<note n="*" place="margin">Iniq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam regna, perptuo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. <hi>Senec. in Med.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Peacefull Rule:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No Realme is read, t'haue Rul'de bin heretofore,</l>
               <l>By ſuch a <hi>Queene,</hi> ſafe quelling Ciuile Brule;</l>
               <l>VVho raigning ſtill, a Prince withouten peere;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her highnes</hi> now, holds on her <hi>Thirtieth yere.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Adore <hi>Nouembers</hi> ſacred<note n="*" place="margin">More fit to be ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other dayes noted in the Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender.</note> 
                  <hi>Sev'nteenth Day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVherein our <hi>Second Sunne</hi> began her Shine:</l>
               <l>Ring out lowd ſounding Bels; on Organs play;</l>
               <l>To Muſikes Mirth, let all Eſtates incline:</l>
               <l>Sound Dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, &amp; Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets, renting Ayre &amp; Ground</l>
               <l>Stringd Inſtruments, ſtrike with Melodious ſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye Mightie Men of <hi>Mars</hi> ennobled <hi>Knights,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aduaunce your ſelues, on fiery foming ſteedes:</l>
               <l>Reuiue <hi>This Tymes</hi> Remembrance, with all Rights,</l>
               <l>In Armour bright, and gorgeous warlik weedes:</l>
               <l>At <hi>Tylt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Turnay,</hi> trying Martiall Might;</l>
               <l>And Battring ſtrokes, at <hi>Barriers</hi> forcefull fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye Cuntry folke, foorth ſtalking in your feelds,</l>
               <l>Lowd Carols ſing, to celebrat This Tyme;</l>
               <l>Show Signes of ioy (as Cuntry manner yeldes,)</l>
               <l>In Sporting Games, with Daunce, and rurall Ryme:</l>
               <l>Eche Swayne, and Sheppard, ſound his piping Reede,</l>
               <l>For ioy, enioying <hi>Feelds,</hi> &amp; <hi>Flocks</hi> to feede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye <hi>Bryttiſh Poets,</hi> Repeat in Royall Song,</l>
               <l>(VVith waightie woords, vſde in King <hi>Arthurs</hi> daies)</l>
               <l>Th'<hi>Imperiall Stock,</hi> from whence your <hi>Queene</hi> hath ſprong;</l>
               <l>Enſtall in verſe your <hi>Princeſſe</hi> laſting prayes:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Maſters in the Science of Muſick.</note>
                  <hi>Pencerddiaid,</hi> play on Auncient Harp, and Crowde:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Expert men in ſinging.</note>
                  <hi>Atceiniaid,</hi> ſing her prayſes pearcing lowd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Hilles, &amp; Rocks, rebounding <hi>Ecchoes</hi> yelde,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Queene Elizabeths</hi> long laſting Fame;</l>
               <l>Let woody Groaues, and VVatry Streames be fild,</l>
               <l>And Creeks, &amp; Caues, with ſounding of the ſame:</l>
               <l>O <hi>Cambria,</hi> ſtretch, &amp; ſtraine thy vtmost breth,</l>
               <l>To praiſe, and pray for <hi>Queene Elizabeth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Her <hi>Third tyme Ten yeres Raigne,</hi> we now poſſeſſe;</l>
               <l>Thriſe three times Ten,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> euery faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>god</hi> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t her <hi>grace</hi> may raign</l>
               <l>To this her Realmes long wiſht for wealfulneſse,</l>
               <l>VVhereby, eche long erſt Loſse, it may Regain:</l>
               <l>And ſo Redound, the happieſt Realme for ay,</l>
               <l>Vnturnd from <hi>Truthe,</hi> ev'n till the <hi>Latter Day.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>God Preſerue Queene Elizabeth.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <p>O Hieruſalem praiſe the Lord:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 147.</note> Praiſe thy God, ô Sion. For he hath ſtrengthned the Barres of thy Gates: And hath Bleſſed thy Children within thee. He hath made all thy Borders Peace: And with the good Nutriment of Wheat doth ſatisfie thee, &amp;c. He hath not done thus to euery Nation els: Praiſe we all the Lord therefore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9805:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
